Finding Aid for Woman's Christian Temperance Union. Flint Federation Records 1874-1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Woman's Christian Temperance Union, Flint Federation records 1874-1980
Woman's Christian Temperance Union. Flint Federation (Flint, Mich.)
1.8 linear ft. and 1 oversize volume
85499 BJ 2 BJ outsize
Flint, Michigan chapter of the national Woman's Christian Temperance Union, founded in 1874; includes minutes and other administrative records of Flint chapter and records of several subordiate unions.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This record group (donor 5688 ) was first received in 1975 as part of the Michigan WCTU collection. Additions were received in 1979, 1987, and 1995.
The collection is open for research.
The Flint chapter of the Woman's Christian Temperance Union [WCTU] was founded in 1874, one of the first local unions of the organization in the state. The first meeting of the chapter drew fifty members, and the organization quickly grew to several hundred women and children over the next few years. Numbers were large enough that several separate chapters were formed in the Flint area, with their activities coordinated by the Flint Federation of the WCTU. In addition to the group's main goal, which was to outlaw the sale of alcoholic beverages, WCTU members worked to prevent the sale and distribution of tobacco, narcotics and pornography, and were active in the woman suffrage movement as well.
In 1908, twelve years before the passage of the eighteenth amendment, the Flint WCTU successfully campaigned for Genesee County to vote "dry" in a local option election. This proved to be a high point for Flint WCTU members. With the repeal of Prohibition in 1933, the organization's numbers gradually declined. The group focussed on education campaigns, citizenship programs, and special projects such as sending fruit juice to soldiers overseas.
At the WCTU's height of influence during Prohibition there were two dozen local chapters in Flint and the surrounding county. As the membership aged and fewer young women joined, however, local chapters disbanded, as did the Flint Federation of WCTU chapters during the early 1970s. The remaining chapters continue as part of the Seventh District of the Michigan WCTU.
The Flint WCTU collection is organized in two series, Flint Federation and Flint Local Unions
The Flint WCTU collection comprises 1.8 linear feet and one oversize volume; it spans the years 1874 to 1975 and contains minutes, treasurers' books, correspondence, reports and scrapbooks. The collection includes records from the organization's most successful years, and also documents its diminishing numbers and political clout between the 1930s and 1970s. Of particular interest are minutes from the group's first meeting in 1874, which are located in the oversize volume.
Subjects:
Woman's Christian Temperance Union. Flint Federation (Flint, Mich.); Flint (Mich.); Temperance--Michigan--Flint.; Women--Michigan--Flint--Societies and clubs.
Genre/Form:
Scrapbooks.
- Flint Federation
  - Constitution and By-laws, 1961-1965 (Box 1)
  - Lillian Stevens Day Scrapbook, c.1930-1939 (Box 1)
  - Minutes
    - 1874-1891 (Box 1)
      (outsize volume, stored separately)
    - 1909-1970, 6 volumes (Box 1)
  - Reports and Correspondence, 1938-1940 (Box 1)
- Flint Local Unions
  - Blackwell Union
    - Treasurer's Book, 1964-1975 (Box 1)
  - Central Union
    - Minutes, 1966-1974 (Box 1)
  - Elizabeth Perkins Union
    - Minutes, 1939-1970, 1 folder and 3 volumes (Box 2)
    - Scrapbook, ca. 1942-1952 (Box 2)
  - Frances Willard Union
    - Centennial Scrapbook, 1936 (Box 2)
    - Minutes, 1913-1959, 1 folder and 4 volumes (Box 2)
  - Harmon Union Treasurer's
    - Books and Clippings, 1945-1975 (Box 2)
  - Northside Union
    - Minutes, 1948-1959 (Box 2)
    - Secretary's Books, 1916-1947, 2 volumes (Box 2)